What's going on everyone? Welcome back to another
video with the School of Hard Knocks. I'm James.
I'm here with Jack. We got a very special
guest today. Don does deals. He's a real estate
entrepreneur out here in Central Texas, and he's
been wholesaling real estate for the last few
years. As you can see, man, we're going to break
it down in this video, let you guys know what to
look for, what it takes to get these good
deals and make a lot of money wholesaling properties
out here in San Antonio. What is wholesaling in
your own words? And so I know you guys probably
hear the word wholesaling thrown all around,
investor, real estate investor, but here is
basically what it is. Basically what you're doing
is you're selling a contract, right? So you're
going to acquire a deal and then you're going
to sell that deal to an investor that's looking to
flip without doing the work. So what it does
is essentially is you mitigate the work that's being
done because you're not doing any of the
work. You're basically getting that contract for a good
enough price and you're selling it to an investor where
he's able to flip it, do the rehab, and both
of you guys are able to still make money.
Why are typically most of the properties that go
into wholesale, they're typically like distressed or they're
not, you know, kind of like super up
to date or like remodeled like properties. Why
is that typically the case? Okay. So great question.
That primarily is because you can't get
loans on these properties, right? So it
probably is because you can't get loans on
these properties. So it probably is because you can't
get loans on these properties. So it probably
is because you can't get loans on these properties.
If the properties need work, the banks won't
finance on them. So what does that mean? So
since they can't be financed on, then cash buyers have
to come in and do the work. And so once the
work's done, then you can take loans on them
and those types of things. So that's why the cash
buyers are so great in these scenarios, because as you
see this property here, you can see it has a
pool. You can see that, you know, the property
is actually in a great community. It's just the
property just needs a little TLC, what we call,
you know what I mean? A little work. Yeah. And
so that's why we talk about the ARV, right?
I know you probably guys probably heard that term. That's
after this home is rehabbed, then that's what it's
going to be worth. Once the flooring, the carpet,
the kitchen's updated, because as you guys can
see, this kitchen's probably 30, 40 years old.
You can see no granite, no updates on it.
You know, you can see the chandelier here. This thing
is, you know, out of date. But as you know,
like once you come in here and rehab it, you know,
update these flooring, this house can be totally
turned around. How can just the average person
that doesn't really know anything about wholesaling
start finding these deals? There's tons of
properties in Texas. There's tons of properties all
over the country. How do they really go out
and find the properties that need work
done? Primarily, the first step is going to
be driving for dollars, right? You can get
around, you can drive, you can actually get in
your vehicle and drive around and see properties
that need work. Also, you can look at properties
that maybe there's not a lot of action there.
So like they're vacant. For example, like I always
tell people this is a little trick too. Like maybe
you get to a property, you don't see nobody taking
the trash out for a while. Or, you know, you
may see trash in the front or you may, basically you
see that the property has not been any upkeep. And
so after that, what you can do is you can do
research on that property to see if that property
is vacant, if the owner's around, you know, maybe
the owner's died, whatever the case may be.
Now, when you were first kind of like getting
into wholesaling, was there a lot of that for
you as far as like properties that weren't listed?
Were you reaching out to properties potentially? And
like, did you have any success in finding
deals through that? Yeah, yeah, yeah. So there's
data, basically there's services you can pay for
where they'll basically give you a list of data
where you can call people. That's when you do the
legwork. So there's ways to do that too. But
for a typical person starting off with no money,
no resources, the driving for dollars is going to
be answered. As you scale up and as you,
you know, get in the business, then you
get into purchasing data and things like that. But
for the person on ground zero, driving for dollars,
see these properties that need work, see these
distressed properties, and then you get in contact
with them. And a lot of times you're going to
see some of the properties, they will be on the market.
So what you can do is you can get in
contact with those agents and those agents will let you know,
hey, this property, here's the price, here's this, here's
that, you know what I mean? You kind of go
from there. When you do find a property that
you like and you want to put under contract,
what does your pricing process look like when you
determine like, hey, this is how much I want to
sell it to the cash buyer for, this is how much
I want to make off this property. How do you know
how much you can price it for? Yeah, so
it's a simple formula. That's probably by far the most
important piece. Because if you get the property too
high, you don't make no money. So you have to
know how to analyze the property. You have to
run comparables, right? So I have to know like this
property behind me, what I have to do is I
have to compare this property to a property just like
this. If this property next door sold for a
certain price in the last month, then I can use
that as my comparable, right? So I know after
all the rehab is done, this property can go for
this amount, right? So you finally find that
property and you analyze that, hey, this is
going to be a good deal for you. How do
you put that under contract? Okay, so yeah, you're going
to put it under contract, under a standard contract.
You know, that's used for any resale of a
property. And then you're going to get it under
contract with that seller. Now, is there any money
that you have to put down in that process?
Oh, earnest money. You just got to put
earnest money down with the seller. Usually it's 1%.
But it fluctuates just depending on your seller.
Sometimes it could be higher, sometimes it could
be lower. And all that earnest money is, is
just to secure that you're serious. They say you have
some skin in the game. And that just means
like, because you got to understand there's a lot of
people out here wholesaling, you know, from their couch
and they don't, you know, and so that just
lets people know, look, this guy's serious. He's got
some skin in the game. And that just means,
he's serious about buying the property.
Because once you put it under contract,
you have to understand that that property is
then tied up for a certain period of time.
They cannot sell that property to anybody else
while it's under contract with you. And that's
the most important thing. So once you
have it under contract, that's the first step,
the most important step. And that's when you
can go ahead and get started, you know,
moving on down the line to kind of
find your cash buyer and things like that.
Once you have it under contract, who do you
work with? Is that, it's called a title company?
Is that right? So how do you find the title
company? How do you, how do you work with them
pretty much? Yeah. So, I mean,
finding a title company is relatively easy.
They're not going to be able to find a title
company. They're going to be able to find a title
company. There's tons of title companies that work
with wholesalers. So that's just a matter of
getting on Google, finding a title company that
works with wholesalers. And you'll find that some
title companies are more investor or wholesaler friendly.
And that's the ones that you want to
work with. It's usually in your local area. Yeah, your
local area. You want to do it in your local
area. Some title companies are done online and
things like that. But me personally, I like to
work with title companies where I can go there, I can
talk to them. You know, I can be face to face
with them just in case anything goes
down. So basically like cash buyer, there's somebody
with a lot of money, a lot of private money.
You don't have to go to the bank. Basically someone
you can work with. They want to invest
in real estate themselves. Why should they pay you?
They're paying me because I found a property at such
a discount. I was able to make money and I'm
able to save them money. So like I always tell
people, if you get the property at a good enough
price, the investor is going to make a ton
of money once he flips it. This property is going
to sell to an investor for about $235,000. The
ARV on it, the after repair value is $350,000.
And this property probably needs about $30,000, $35,000
worth. All in for $270,000 and you can
sell it for $350,000. Awesome. So how much would
you essentially make off this in a wholesale fee?
So normally we want to do about $20,000.
We do like a $20,000 wholesale fee on this one.
There you go. $20,000 easy, just like that.
Off of one property. Dom's been giving us some
crazy games so far. Make sure that you leave us
a like and subscribe. We got tons of
crazy content coming and stick around to the end
because Dom's going to put us on how to
really find these cash buyers and get you some money.
Like all the different chandeliers in this property.
Yeah. So Dom, my next question would be,
you've been wholesaling real estate for the last three
years. What is the biggest deal
that you've done to this point?
Okay. So biggest deal, I think we did...
I did a 13 property package. Quick back story on
that. I had a guy, right? Ex-military. I was able
to really connect with him. He had 13 properties
that he wanted to offload because he wanted to
go into a commercial business. So we were able
to get that property, get it under contract and find
a buyer. And I think the wholesale assignment fee
on that was like $150,000. We were able to
get that thing done and we're doing multi-million dollar
deals on the iPhone. So I always make that
joke, million dollar deal on the iPhone.
That's one deal and that's more than most
people make in a year. That's pretty crazy.
It just kind of goes to show the
power with real estate and kind of the wholesaling
in general is, it's an unreal game right now.
Is wholesaling primarily just residential or
can you also do wholesaling with commercial
contracts as well? Yeah. You can wholesale commercial
contracts as well. We have a few people
that work with... I don't do it personally,
but I know people locally in the
area that are wholesaling commercial property. It's different.
It's a whole different dynamic. But to answer
your question in lamest terms, yes, you can
wholesale commercial property. Can anybody really get started
wholesaling? How old do you have to be?
I can get started wholesaling. I mean, like I
was talking to you guys about earlier, you have
17, 18 year old multi-millionaires
from wholesaling. It's a real thing.
It's incredible because it's just like most people think
real estate, oh, I'm an agent. So I help
people find their home to buy or like I'm
an investor. I'll either put money in to build the
property up and flip it or I'm just going to
like put money in and get cashflow. You don't even have
to have a license to do this, do
you? No, you don't. It doesn't require a license.
It doesn't require a license. You can get
started right away. You know, you've been doing wholesaling
for a couple of years now. What has
been the biggest challenge that you've faced? You know,
anybody can get into wholesaling, but it's a
simple process, but it can't all be bells and
whistles. It's got to be some challenge that
you face. It really comes down to like the
entrepreneurial aspect of like, you know, you have
nobody like looking behind you. A lot of things
you have to figure out on the go.
Dealing with these sellers, building rapport, getting these
contracts, learning different tools about the real
estate, running comps. I mean, it's a lot
of things that go into it. It's a very
simple process, but it's a grind. Is there any challenge
specifically that you've faced? Just sticking to it,
learning the business and just sticking to it
and just going to go. Like, because a lot
of times things are going to be changing. Things are
going to be all over the place, but you got
to get in this business and do what works for you.
You know what I mean? Because everyone's going
to have different ideas. There's a ton of different
gurus online telling you how to do stuff. But once
you figure out what works for you, I think that's
the key. It's basically the learning curve. Yeah, exactly.
Why would you not just want to flip the
property yourself? Like, why would you go
through the process of wholesaling their real estate?
Yeah. I mean, there's a few different reasons.
The primary reason is the liability of property. So
when you're wholesaling, you just basically getting
the contract, selling it to someone else,
and you're not taking on
all responsibility. That's the primary
reason. The second reason is just funding. A
lot of times when you're hopping into this stuff,
you know, especially if you're young, you don't have
the funding to do the rehab. You may not have
the funding. You may not have the credit. You may not
be, you know, stable to do it. So you want to
do the wholesaling to sort of generate revenue and
so you can become an actual investor. All right,
guys. Dom just showed us basically step-by-step how
to find these homes, analyze them, put it
under contract, and basically go get paid by
finding a cash buyer and selling it. So Dom,
hey, thank you so much, man, for taking us
out to this property, bro, and being able to show
everybody how they can get started and
start making six figures wholesaling and real estate.
How can people find you?
Yeah, they can find me.
They can find me on IG. DomDoesDeals4Real.
Yeah, any wholesalers getting into the one,
hop into this space. You know, you may
have some deals you need help with, you know,
reach out to me. I got a network of guys behind
me, a team that, you know, we can get deals done.
So if you guys are out there, you're looking
to get into this space, looking to make some money,
looking to make some moves, trust me, real estate is
where it's at, man. You guys tap in with me.
Oh, yeah. Thank you guys, everyone, for tuning in
to another video with the School of Hard Knocks.
James, Jack, Dom Does Deals. Make
sure you like, leave a subscribe,
and stay tuned for some bigger content on the way.
Thank you.